Ladies and gentlemen, thank you very much for coming today and being willing to brave
the mid-afternoon trap that is Santa Monica for our forum.
My name is Kevin Cloud and I'm managing director of the California Center here at the Milken
Institute and I want to welcome you today on a forum we're doing in partnership with
Los Angeles Times on the key topic of open data.
So thank you everyone for coming, I'm sure it's going to be a very enlightening and insightful
conference on a topic that on the surface sounds somewhat simple but is in fact very
important and to discuss for a minute what makes this topic so significant, I'm going
to hand over the microphone to my colleague Jason Barrett.
Thank you Kevin, my name is Jason Barrett, I am a policy analyst with the Milken Institute.
I just want to say a quick word or two about the importance of open data to the Institute
and also to the state of California.
There are three main issues that the Institute has examined when it comes to open data.
The first is government transparency.
It's a very important issue, voters want to know where their money is going and they feel
that they have a right to know.
The second is government effectiveness.
It's not just a matter of helping Californians understand their government, it's about helping
the California government understand itself.
Interagency cooperation is very important from any number of issues regarding permitting,
secret reform, there are a lot of needless delays that come from an overarching bureaucracy
within a government that is the size of Californians.
And the third topic is economic development opportunities.
One of our panelists today is from Trulia which is a real estate company that has really
kind of led the way in terms of using open data to create a software platform and create
a huge company out of it and that's just one example.
So without further ado I will hand it over to our moderator.
He is the editor of the LA Times data desk.
He is one of the leading journalists in open data in California and he's written several
articles about the need for open data in California.
Ben Welsh.
Ben.
Hello.
Hi everybody.
Thank you for coming out on a Wednesday afternoon, we really appreciate it.
I think we're going to be talking here as a group as a discussion for about one hour
and then you'll have the opportunity to send in your questions to the address they post
up and we'll read those, I'll read those off to the panel when that time comes too.
Okay.
So to kick things off I just want to introduce the four guests here.
The first is Deep Varma.
He is a vice president of data engineering at Trulia which is a real estate website I
bet it's pretty popular here in Santa Monica.
You can go on there and click around on a map to oversimplify things maybe to the point
of insult.
Click around on a map and look up the recent real estate sales and listings and kind of
track the Southern California's greatest spectator sport and he's an expert in the field of how
you take government data and you turn it into something useful and that people love to interact
with and that ultimately makes money.
Sitting next to him is Secretary of State Alex Padilla who if I can still read a calendar
was elected to office one year ago today.
This is the anniversary of his election to that office.
Obviously as Secretary of State he oversees elections here in the state of California
as well as a number of important data systems which might be called open data relating to
voter registration, the registration of corporations and LLCs and a number of other things.
Prior to being the Secretary of State he was in the California State Senate for I believe
two terms.
He can correct me here and before that was elected city councilman here to represent
the San Fernando Valley at the very young age of 26 where you grew up.
Is that correct?
Is it Angelino?
Born and raised.
Great.
Next up is Alicia Ruo who is a senior advisor to the president of a group called Code for
America.
Does everybody here know what Code for America is?
No.
Okay it's a very cool non-profit organization that partners with local governments and state
and larger governments too all across America to bring in young bright techie people into
government offices and help them kind of do things a different way, introduce talent,
introduce new techniques for making software both by bringing in the talent and at the
higher level advising people on how to get stuff done.
And so she's a very important person there.
And then next to her is Ted Ross another very important person who is the chief information
officer for the city of Los Angeles which means he's the general manager and department
head of a whole big section of city government that runs tons and tons of software that can
range from boring stuff like email and payroll all the way to really exciting cutting edge
stuff like open data portals and the body cameras that are going to go on all the LAPD
officers as well.
And so these four are you know going to be the stars of the show here and I'm just going
to ask them a bunch of questions and hopefully we'll have a great conversation.
Does that sound good?
Love it.
Okay so even though I'm a nerd and I work at this nerdy thing called the data desk and
write code all day I still am kind of a reporter at heart right and so I have my little notes
here and I want to open with the news.
So I don't know if you all heard but Governor Jerry Brown signed two new open data bills
last month.
One AB 169 which is now law requires that all data published online by California state
by California governments has to be published in something called an open format that's
easily downloadable can be picked up and parsed and reused by humans and by the computer programming
scripts that humans write to do things for them.
The second bill SB 272 getting this right I hope requires all the agencies in addition
to that to create a list an index they call it of all the different data systems that
the particular agency runs and then publish that list online right and so these two bills
which are now law as of about a little less than a month ago are being hailed by the activists
and people who are pushing open data as an idea as landmark legislation you know open
formats for the data and a list of databases.
Now if you're not a techie person in this world this might not sound like that big a deal
right well how big a deal is a list of databases but it really is and I want to first off ask
the secretary to explain it like why is this legislation quote unquote landmark why does
it matter what are what what's the big deal.
What's the big deal I guess for technologists it may seem pretty straightforward simple
kind of common sense but it's certainly significant culture change I think on behalf of government
you know we can debate what the expectations were pre Nixon post Nixon information sharing
you know what led to things like the Freedom of Information Act and Public Records Act
and those sorts of things but the bottom line is government by and large got into the mindset
of you know everything you don't want to make a mistake so don't share information that
you're not compelled to for fear of making a mistake all right there's certain there
is reason for some things to not be shared privacy protection security protections etc.
But I think where government law side of the fundamental premise that public information
is public information and it ought to be easily available and usable by the public and with
the advances in technology it was no longer or will fulfill your request and now sends
us 10 cents per page so we can make photocopies of stuff right we can now share electronically
post electronically and the fundamental mindset shift is wait a minute let's not the default
be we're going to hold on to data unless we're compelled to share if there if there isn't
a reason to want to hold on to let's make it readily available that seems kind of obvious
why is that why is a law necessary I think a law was necessary a because the culture
shift hasn't completely played out and so sometimes you need that directive or or that
requirement on the part of city department city county state departments and agencies
to share that information otherwise they were choosing not to but I think you know we can have
a longer conversation about what the upside is of having that data more readily available both for
other government users for individuals for app developers and everybody in between okay I mean
now deep you are you work at a company that takes government data and is a raw raw material and
turns it into kind of like a finished product yeah right would something there's a law that
requires an open format help you with that and explain what an open format is and how it would
impact the kind of work that you guys are doing yeah so definitely truly a lead by an example on
this and we saw a challenge from a consumer point of view I still remember 1999 when I bought my
first house it is you know I spent months and months going through the documents and looking
into you know neighborhood looking into the crime score looking into the past transactions and you
know collecting all the pieces of the documents sitting with my wife going over all the things
and it the journey was a meaningful journey but at the end it is a time which I could have spent
better with my family we saw that how we can use all this data which is lying around because if
the data is an information information is the power what we all need so if the data is lying
there on the pages I have to read the pages but can technology help us use these documents
transform into a more structured information make it in the way that it is searchable so when we
thought we thought from a consumer point of view when consumer comes to Trulia consumer comes and
says you know this is what I'm looking for and we provide this data which is which is you know
when I sit with my engineers on a day-to-day basis it is a millions of the rows of the data which is
coming into our database it's not that simple so we have to run the pipelines and the hours of
processing to make it meaningful meaningful to us so too I think overall for the industry this
open format or the open data allows us to focus on where we want to focus on so rather than
focusing on getting this 20 files and making them into one format and then spending all our time I
will rather if I know all this data coming to Trulia is it in a consistent format it is a quality
of a data it is a fresh data then I would rather focus more towards consumer and make this
information the crime data the neighborhood data the school information the transit information
make it more easily accessible to the consumers so that's what I feel those two you know bills
are the step in the right direction but it's still we are scratching the surface we have to go way
more than that before even we see the benefits out of that and we'll get to that now Alicia now if
governments aren't publishing data in open formats now what are they doing well many governments
love the pdf and while that seems like does everybody know what a pdf is okay so it's it's
a step better than paper that I honestly need to boo go ahead you know releasing pdfs is a great
gesture toward opening and releasing information but when you're a programmer and if we think about
the way that data is actually used it's used in applications it's used in queries if it's not
actually readable by a machine it's not useful so part of the law that was passed is a part in it
that says it needs to be machine readable which means that computers can actually parse it
there's a great example in the city of portland one of the the first ways data was really made
open in the united states was around transit data there's a transit and i deep kind of just
referred to transit data as being an important data set portland's transportation commission
called trimet released their data and they did so under a specification which simply just means
it's standardized it has specific columns field names and they're consistent and this was sort
of the format that the rest of the united states through google actually started publishing their
transit data so when we talk about the word standard that's what we mean is it's produced
consistently and published consistently so that machines can actually process it yeah so that's
why i can use my google maps to find out the bus schedule and the and the traffic anywhere in
america but i can't do the same thing for crime or for other things that deep mention that's right
now ted at the city of la you guys have already taken a lot of steps along the road that these
laws kind of point to right uh why don't you share with the audience what what the city's done
certainly so i have the honor of serving mayor eric garcetti and so uh the fact that probably
most of the folks in the room don't know while he was a then council member running for the mayor's
office he was actually as a council member pushing a council motion through council to
try to be able to launch an open data portal and to do a lot more when it came to providing open
government i think the reason why is he you know philosophically completely agrees it's the citizens
government and it truly is citizens data and there's the ability of capturing so much opportunity
because there's things that government does well and there's things that obviously private
sector non-profits do well so why not let government which has a monopoly in many ways on
the data there's truly data that only government has why not partner that data so long as it's
responsible and doesn't it doesn't violate any security issues or personal individual rights
etc social security numbers those types of things why not partner government's greatest asset in its
data partner that with private sector which is innovating and non-profits which are researching
and then you can get a very powerful a very powerful force a nexus of forces if you will
in which you can get a lot more services delivered to the citizen i think it's a great example here
with real estate information with other aspects it allows government to deliver a service not
directly i kind of liken it to a point guard in basketball you know the point guard doesn't do all
the scoring but they often push the ball around they feed it to other people so they can score
they do assist this is a way for government to assist others and at the city of los angeles
we did a lot when it came to getting across our city government all sorts of different data sets
and making them available and more than just publishing them in a portal really seeking ways
to engage people so partnering with folks like google so that ways data would have city information
regarding street closures and all sorts of things that improve the users for that app or partnering
with others to be able to deliver that information going to hackathons right where programmers will
get together and they'll hack on certain topics we have huge issues around things like a drought
in southern california so let's bring a group together and let's get data from our department
of water and power and others to be able to start hacking on that and so it's trying to identify
ways to really engage universities around traffic and traffic collision information we did that
recently and all sorts of other developers so it's more than just making data available in which that
will capture one group of people but is actually making data available consumable and finding those
who are interested to do really good things with that uh so now that this law is passed people who
aren't as up to speed as you that need a law to get them to do it are going to be challenged to
kind of like make it happen right so lisha you've seen the inside of a lot of different governments
in your work with code for america right that's right so what is it that stops governments from
making progress on this front um i think there's a lot of reasons why open data is is hard to get
started with um if you think about top-down leadership um that's not always present there's
not always the case to open data um luckily l.a has leadership that is you know very much in
support of opening data as does santa monica so why would it in all fairness yes so no so why
would a government be against that doesn't open data sound good guys how could you oppose that
well i think it's sometimes hard to trace sort of the the roi the immediate return on opening this
information um and i think opening data to open for opening data's sake is not necessarily the
right way to go um we did some work in alba kirky uh and and there one of the um the folks that
worked in the it department um really had to struggle to make the case to his leadership
that um opening data would be a good thing for the city his criteria was that if you can't trace it
down to an actual consumer or an end user that will benefit from it it's not worth opening
and i think that that sort of criteria is a way to help governments open information when
transparency isn't necessarily working so what would an example of that be so he worked on
reducing the number of 311 calls into the city so it was an efficiency play um he said you know if
you open the 311 data and we can see where the complaints are coming time after time spatially
geographically um we can actually reduce the number of complaints that we get to the city
and it worked it actually reduced the number of complaints that came in and so then he got
promoted and he's the general manager like ted no no oh go ahead i don't know i have an interesting
example that you referenced 311 and trying to create a more efficient 311 because the very
existence of 311 systems was trying to take the the load and inefficiencies out of a 911 system
and so i just can't help but recognize how far we actually have come
government is not perfect we have a long way to go but in the last 20 years alone
we had uh you know 911 overburdened you know thank baltimore for really pioneering
but the 311 system former police chief bill bratton here in la who's back in new york is
a police commissioner there really sort of uh thinking more more more digitally analytically
developing a comp step model right using data to drive decisions on how you deploy resources to try
to both minimize crime prevent crime etc which then sponsor the city stats and more comprehensive
governments uh in general conversations about using data you know internally so there's just
been this evolution you know government internally using data to make better decisions and investments
and i think given where technology is now the ability to share that data with other partners
to tap the innovative juices that we have not just in california but to utilize this data in in ways
that you know no one person in government knows it all but we've come a long way i think the last 20
years and you know i think the curve is exponentially increasing and how much more we're
going to see at all i'm going to pass this i think so open data is mind shift that's the
most important thing we just cannot go just with the bills and say okay we have passed the two
bills but there's a mind shift and on top of the mind shift i think so it's it's we just cannot
leave the open data and say it's always for the betterment of the transparency i think so it's an
effectiveness what is the effectiveness for the government for the states for the counties how
can we serve our consumers or our people better and faster i think is that the what i feel is it's
the the bottleneck here is the bill's been passed but what's the driving value what's who's going
to drive this forward certainly i local agency go and publish all my enterprise systems so i think
is that mind shift needs to happen and to me is bill is a step in that direction where i think
california is doing an amazing job by passing the bill but i think is we need to have the
leaders those who help us like you know ted is doing in this shift the mindset and say that why
this is important so that's the critical piece too and i mean that's really one of the goals of
code for america right is to introduce those different types of thinking and people who think
that way and come from this silicon valley world into government but i guess ted ted why is that
necessary do you guys have is is you know if the city of l.a when they open up job applications
for to be a firefighter i love to write about the fire department it's one of my hobby horses
there'll be 70 jobs and 10 000 people will apply right oh the vast majority of whom are probably
well qualified for the job and very eager to take it why does government struggle to attract talent
to kind of help it build capacity to bring in new blood and need something like code for america
well it some of it comes down philosophically to where government often sees itself
so you find that governments get very busy doing things and as you start reducing staff you start
reducing budget i i serve in department i manage a department that's lost 40 of staff in the last
six years so since the great recession we're a very much smaller department which makes us
reprioritize also a lot of things and when open data becomes in as a conversation all too often
it gets interpreted it shows up on the radar is look here's another thing we're being required
to do when i've got all these other systems and all these you know police or fire department
systems i'm maintaining and now i've got this one more thing put on my plate and so i think
sometimes it gets misunderstood and misinterpreted so at the city of los angeles it becomes really
critical to have that philosophical shift to have that change honestly and this is someone coming
from inside government one of the greatest benefits of open data i'm a firm believer in
transparency i'm an angelina i'm a firm believer in transparency i'm a firm believer in open
government but the application of everything you do with open data inside of government is also
beneficial so you'd be surprised how much data is not being shared between departments let alone
with the public right you know i i implemented a financial system in which quite often you were
figuring out we were instructed from all these different department managers on ways to keep
other departments from seeing your budget and so they're trying to figure out ways of building all
these modifications so we can't see each other's data when the reality is obviously we should be
sharing it even with others so it becomes something fundamentally important for us to
share data across departments to create what they call apis interfaces between data so that
systems and machines can go ahead and integrate data between each other so open data is a very
powerful movement and a very powerful concept that you can apply across so many different areas
we get all sorts of requests for information if that's saying if i identify the types of requests
for information i get and put it as self-service you don't have to ask me anymore right so there's
all these ways of making government more efficient by putting it out there and and really to address
ben's question often at the city of los angeles and often in government we get too stuck in the
day-to-day we get too stuck in what we were delivering last week and and a very large
workload and when we really need to be stepping out of it and thinking more strategically
if i'm busy processing public records requests i really need to maybe take a step back and say
what's a mechanism or a method so i don't have to be processing these and that you could go get
them in a very easy to understand a reasonable format and i think one of the other uh under
appreciated upsides of open data and the movement for it is based on the assumption that government
has good quality data clean data organized data that's right right and so the expectations we'll
just share it just share it just share it because we want to unleash you know innovation and
all the brilliant ideas that will come as a result so so don't overestimate the quality
or organization of our data but on the other hand keep the pressure on because that is pushing all
areas of government and all levels of government to to upgrade and modernize and and improve the
secretary hit the nail on the head once i have to start publishing data i'll take a step and look
at it and say and i i don't really mean me but a department will take a look at it and say
boy the quality of this data really isn't quite right which begs the question why do you have data
that is of poor quality are you running your operation off of poor quality data so i like
just about every question involved with open data i like the idea that if you have to publish it
it needs to be good and if it's not good let's make it good and that just improves everything
it's true you know i don't use the expression very often i truly do see a lot of win-win when it
comes to an open government open data type of conversation you know the whole idea of open data
it all sounds great and it sounds new maybe to people who haven't heard it before but it's really
not new right you know this is an initiative that president obama came into office trumpeting and
gosh that was nearly eight years ago now and he's preparing to leave office and you know i'm kind of
you know how much progress can we really claim when i really when you think about it in that
time period we've had a lot of panel discussions like this we've had a lot of little laws we've
had a lot of fellows go out right but we've also we've also had healthcare.gov happen
right we've had uh the state's unemployment check system fail to the point that it can't send them
out we have the secretary state's office still struggling with many large it projects to push
through that you inherited when you came into office is this stuff like really moving the needle
or is it or is it is it is it still more rhetoric than results mr secretary okay it's probably a
combination right it's um so let's understand one dynamic intention here uh to oversimplify
we have silicon valley right i mean innovation is happening on a daily basis
stuff is advancing stuff is progressing stuff is constantly getting better
public policy right how a bill becomes a law goes a little bit slower uh so whether it's policy
law statute regulation etc it doesn't move nearly as fast as the pace of innovation so it comes
so there's always going to be this this tension and this trouble i'd like to point out at least one
i think a quick win uh in my first year in office and it was part a public finance transparency
accountability win and part not so much a technological advance but you know i think
a huge win in sort of bypassing the traditional it procurement process in the state of california
others would call it the traditional it procurement quagmire in the state of california
when we were willing to share data which opened to everybody on campaign finance who's raising
money from who map light the organization map light through found private foundation funding
was able to put together a much better search engine for who's raising money from who developed
this tool called power search which they were willing to you know gift to the state of california
we integrated into our secretary of state's website so think about that in the course of
months not years at no cost of taxpayer dollars there's all of a sudden an open source based much
you know new and improved search function for the public and the press to track those campaign
dollars but unfortunately it's the exception to the rule because if you google state of california
it project and hit news you know not a lifetime of 100 it's a bad news story not a good news
right but in that case you essentially solved it by giving up right and having someone else do it
for you i mean can the government not build the capacity to build a website that works we didn't
give up we we found a third way we partnered with somebody and you know during the course of my
campaign people uh proposed y'all ought to get out of that business of you know sharing uh or
posting campaign finance data just let somebody who knows what they're doing kind of take it over
but shouldn't the state know how to do these things yeah we we do and and we can again my first year
in office state of california was the first state in the nation to have a public website with all
this information available that was a good news the bad news we hadn't really upgraded it or updated
it since uh so you know we're on it now but at least in the short term we can do these piecemeal
things that being data driven you know calaxas makes a lot of things possible but the vast
majority of what people go to it for is this campaign contribution tracking so let's focus
on that let's at least upgrade that piece first quickly while we buy time and tackle the rest of
the pieces uh in the coming years i mean alicia you've worked with a lot of governments what do
you think of that model the idea that the government lets kind of somebody else manage a lot of it and
they just lay they put the date on the porch and see who runs off with it well so code for america
is probably an example of in a third party partnering with government to make it better
and so i would say that that model definitely works particularly in a situation where
government is not quite ready to change or do it itself um code for america has this model where
we bring in that silicon valley talent for a year of public service and that year of public service
is really the only amount of time that somebody making six figures at google would actually want
to spend working in government but they come and they do their public service it's a little bit
what we call peace corps for geeks um and we embed uh engineers and designers and product people
into government itself and so they build technology and they process math and they
ultimately pursue a model called user-centered design what's that user-centered design is making
the citizen the customer at the center of every choice that's made so if you think about this
from a service delivery perspective let's say that you want to start a new business
and you go to get a permit filed that's a customer transaction that you have with your government
and so what we do is we take different business transactions in government we map them out and
then we try to solve some of the clunkier paper-based processes through technology
and so that it's interesting there's a couple interesting things i heard there one
obviously was the the six figure thing she quoted did you guys hear that
so um you know um deep i just out of curiosity i'm going to probe here so you oversee a large
engineering team of people who basically and i'm going to oversimplify i'm a reporter they pay me
to oversimplify right who basically take the government data from all the different county
governments who keep those assessor databases and merge them together into one big fancy system and
do it and they're doing that ugly work of working with the data how much do how many people does it
take to do that at trulia and how much does someone who does that work like a frontline person get
paid yeah so i think it's uh we all know silicon valley is silicon valley for a reason right and
this is where the problems comes and we come together and we solve problem and we move fast
and think about the scale right so the scale is there and before i go to this it'll be tough for
me to answer the numbers like who how much people make there but it's you know being in i think is
the how much it's it's all about the problem when you think about google you go back 12 years back
it's all the websites were there all the websites were there standing as a siloed version where
you as a consumer have to go and know about this but google came and changed the mindset
where it started building the indexes started crawling indexing making it searchable and now
guess what even my 11 year old son and my 16 year old son their life goes with the google if they
don't find from dad and mom they go to google it right so this is a great example of why silicon
valley is this and why silicon valley people paid high because you know they solve the problem they
scale it now what it takes to get the data it's all about the scale when we look into
trulia has millions of consumers coming to trulia we have 33 counties across us where we collect
the data on a daily basis someone selling home someone buying home it's all this data is scattered
in a very different formats so what does it mean it means someone needs to understand this data
there are times we are lucky enough to say oh this data means this you know a means this b means
this and there are times you don't know so once we understand the data this is where technology
and the computer are helpful where human beings don't need to sit and do manually we tell computers
when you see this you do that so within the data engineering organization within trulia we have
close to 50 engineers and their job is acquisition of the 50 five zero okay yeah and this is but still
when you look into five zero 50 engineers serving millions of consumers so it is not that we are
talking about 500 just 50 engineers came together and they took all the data where we are serving
and solving that problem for millions and millions of consumers and paying it's basically you know
silicon agriculture has always been risk and reward right i've been in two of my own startups
you go you find a problem you solve a problem and if you solve a problem in a right way you
get rewarded sure but i mean these government the government budgets and systems are as big or bigger
than trulia what prevents the state of california from solving the problem from building the 50
person team from making it happen i think it's so first is which i said clearly is is the mind
shift i think is the mind shift and there has to be more partnership between private and the public
sectors and when i am in silicon valley for so many years traffic is not bad as la but the traffic
in the silicon valley roads are crazy and every time i hear oh the president of this country is
visiting silicon valley to go to google the president of this country is going to facebook
when there are people coming from the outside of us coming to the silicon valley to get the help
that partnership needs to evolve more that how come silicon valley is solving those problems much
faster as compared to and it's i'm not saying there is no desire from public sector not to
solve that it is the partnership needs to come together where we need to come this is where
court for america is helping a lot and i think is defining that partnership is critical and at
the same time this laws are going to help mind shift and then government officials needs to stand
up and say guys the open data defining what the open data means so it's not just a one simple
solution we need to bring all the forces together to solve that so that's where i think is collaboration
between the two silicon valley and the government officials coming together and saying this is how
we're going to scale it and how we're going to solve it hmm that's a point of a key feature
of truly most people will think oh we're going to develop this there's this great new real estate app
and all the information that would sort of support that of course it's land value you know interest
rates you know projected mortgage costs when was the last time it sold yeah what's the price history
on a property i don't know what your analytics tell you but from my experience and a lot of my
friends you know when you find a listing that catches your eye if it's not the second thing
you click on it's the first how do the schools in that area rank yeah right but that's not based on
real estate data that's based on school district information that once upon a time probably wasn't
shared you know and once upon a time was probably only begrudgingly shared with parents that really
insisted right because you know the or newspapers that sued i would point out right but now you know
through a real estate app all of a sudden it's it's readily available and very useful context
maybe i'm wrong no no you know that's a no that's i think that's a fair point you know this is
having this data like commute data the park data there are consumer comes to our side they're
looking for what's the closest park to my home right and this is the data once it becomes public
we are using the technology and empowering our consumer with this data so yeah there was a time
in 90s when this data was not publicly there now being it is there it is much easier for us to
consume this data but for the value what it brings it to the consumer that's a fair point
okay so silicon valley has the solution this is an answer we think we hear pretty frequently
right and one solution i love from silicon valley this is one of the quirky ones is that we could
we could set up some a new country out in the ocean on like a floating platform which would
be free of many of the existing regulations and problems and i mean so let's say ted that that
the deep here financed your effort to build a new new city off the coast of california
right and you had to begin again would have a problem begin again from the start and you
didn't have to remake and you could start a city from scratch and get all this stuff right
what would you do how would it happen different wow that's a that's a fundamental question
you know one i think one thing that's interesting about it and you know i did an mba and so i can't
help but looking at things that way is often you've got different companies in the industry you've
got competitive advantages and so silicon valley has a very powerful competitive advantage and i
and might i say silicon beach in downtown la right technology is occurring as much in many
ways in southern california as it is up there but the reality is tech the tech sector is great in
the sense that they're highly innovative they put their skin in the game and if the product doesn't
sell and it doesn't truly add value you're out of business right and so that is a very powerful
capitalist model that is churning out tremendous innovations and we're one of the finest countries
in the world to be able to make that happen but if you apply that model to government government
does in many ways have a very different model a very different perspective we are expecting our
civil servants to be responsible and ethical to not accept bribes to not be corruptible to be able
to treat people fairly and equally to be able to consider people who often don't have a voice in
government and so we often see a very different model and i think really what works very well
from my perspective is taking a lot of that powerful civil service ethics and integrity
and loyalty and they deliver that where we are to really truly represent the citizens and businesses
and tourists who come to our city and to match that with the innovation so it's identifying the
right partnerships to open everything up to a tech sector and this is coming from a tech guy
to open everything up to a tech sector is just finding one side of the coin to open everything
up to government say government you just do everything yourself it's just another side of a
coin and we could probably run down various different areas where you truly need to have
an integration you need a facilitation you have to have people who start to play their roles
appropriately government needs to know what it does well a private sector does a lot of things
well non-profits do things well i think the best government is one that facilitates all these
different players to truly take into account the needs of the citizens if i were to if i were to
manage that that you know make believe city you know it's funny coming from someone who's
been in government for some time in the private sector before that that's a very difficult
question i would really have to defer to an elected official i'd have to defer to someone
who helps represent the people and and and that's even the other side of it right when we were
implementing open data at the city of la we very quickly saw the roles people played as an it
manager we know the data but don't put us in charge of open data because we're going to see
things from our narrow focus we think they're elected officials are the people who are out in
the streets the people who should have a much better feeling and an understanding of what the
citizens want and what people are asking for so when we kind of looked at the cycle we started to
see elected officials who could represent the people best the people who want the data and then
we could look at technologists who the best people to provide the data in formats that the people who
the elected officials are hearing from should have provided in and then we could also pull in private
sector who had the greatest platforms to make that data available and so we saw very much a
very powerful triad if our elected officials don't participate i don't really hear the will of the
people if the technologists don't participate you're not getting data and if private sector
doesn't participate you're probably getting it in an antiquated useless platform so we often find in
governments about taking the different pieces putting them into their proper roles and really
implementing it that's just my perspective i think that's a great way to describe it because
you describe this potential to create utopia you know and so what would we envision well
you know my background's in engineering i didn't study political science i didn't you know
major in government or anything but that's not my career and so i can tell you if you're going to
start a new society it's going to be a reflection of okay well who's there right and some sort of
process to collectively go through the conversation of okay how are we going to govern ourselves
and once you have some semblance of an institution then what are we going to do what are we going to
contract out for right or we're going to what are we going to partner on and making those deliberate
decisions and different different cities are governed differently whether it's fire and
police protection or technology and everything in between here's a man who's interacted with
citizens you know a thousand times more ten thousand times more than i have and so i'm very
quick to say listen here's a person who's done it and done it well for many years and so i'm
humble and intelligent enough to know that i'd look to him to be able to understand the interactions
with the people and i would expect the same for an elected officials for people who have ten
thousand times the experience on the technology side to be able to bring us in as subject matter
experts when it comes to technology you know i think one of the greatest assets of america is
the fact it was such a diverse group especially here in southern california we're extremely
diverse and we get great power out of that diversity because we've got engineers and we've
got social scientists we've got philosophers and we've got psychologists and we're all really
coming together and we're contributing quite a bit in our own area and i'd like to think that a
utopian city would have a lot of that so maybe for some of the folks watching at home you know
we can talk about open data and open source and quality format of data not pdf but is it
and you said you know that the open data conversation is not a new one when president
obama was elected it was an executive order that was 2009 but raise your hand if you've ever heard
or wondered about police response time everybody has for a long long time that's like a very simple
way of describing what open data is all about imagine the city that wouldn't shovel police
response time was whether it's had a concern for your community there probably are quite a few to
be great or you're looking to buy a house yes probably not so much anymore because of public
demand for that kind of information but i can tell you not police response time but things like
graffiti removal uh or you know firefighter ambulance response and trash pickup you know
statistics when i was at the city i won't name names but there were folks who didn't want to
share that information because it's going to make us look bad right and so this goes back to the
cultural shift no mayor verdon was a leader on this train the whole charter uh reform debate
and the charter reform commissions and your charter being adopted information is good you know you may
not like what it says initially but that's how you create the dynamics where the pressure points come
back to improve i think open data is just a state-of-the-art technology version of that
government accountability and improving government services dynamic with an economic development
opportunity don't we need more for like some of the entrenched interests that do not want data to be
released to be forced to i mean you know just list last year in the united states we've had a
a nationwide outcry over police brutality and shootings across the country and i don't know
if you guys would follow this but there actually are no statistics the numbers are not compiled
or collected about how many people are killed by police across america systematically so the
reality is we just don't know right and the reason we don't know that or we don't know a lot of data
about spree shootings is that there are interest groups in congress and in state governments and
in local governments that oftentimes can prevent certain pieces of information from being released
so for instance i would point out in this inventory law that was just passed if you look
very carefully between the commas like i was trying to do earlier you can see that the local
school districts have been exempted from this law for some reason i don't know but you know that
happened and you can find things like that all across government and in my experience as a reporter
has been and i'm on my soapbox here so forgive me guys my experience as a reporter has been that the
most valuable most sensitive oftentimes most important data is the hardest to get because
there's people who don't want you to have it and so what i hear in a lot of this discussion which i
love and is music to my ears as a nerd is like enlightened smart government people who are saying
we want to make things better and are technocratic in this sort of old school way where they're going
to be good managers who make it happen but can they really control these interest group infections
within the government you know before we talked about open data i'm really going here there was
a thing called the california public records act which really allowed anyone in the public and still
does to request information and the government doesn't have a choice they have to give it right
but at the same time the state government was passing the laws to to loosen this open data
there also was an effort in the legislature i think when you were still there to gut the
california public records act and and not no longer require local governments to meet those
demands directly from the citizens as opposed to ted and the people at the city government getting
to decide what they released and like how do you square that why are how are these two why are these
two winds almost blowing in opposite directions at the same time president obama open data executive
order edward snowden has to go to russia and people who talk to reporters all go to jail
how is it those those two things are happening at the same time that's a great debate there's a
one-man debate right my question for yes i know uh you know the just a quick side note on you know
state uh pra you know statute change of what that was much more a budget issue than not uh
counties that were no longer required there's they're still fulfilling uh the the requirements
at least the spirit and intent but it was a change in language as part of being able to score a
saving in balancing the budget in very very tough tough economic times i don't think jerry brown or
any member of the legislature that voted for the budget you know truly believed we had to go
backwards on uh pra that's that's just you know my side bar there uh but you know the frustration
that you have with while you have some jurisdictions going forward others not wanting to and you know
the exceptions that you may uncover and this and that that's not a technology process that's a
democratic process right that's a that's the result of who's participating who's not who's
what who's weighing in who's not who's you know helping drive public opinion you know who's not
and that's the country that we all live in it requires us all to participate but to come full
circle again open data being a tool to incent that participation and interest from uh the many many
people who appear to have lost him oh i think he did but um okay i mean what so what comes next
i mean so like alicia if you were to say you know this california state legislature needs to take
further steps to push the ball even further down the field what do they need to do um that is also
a big question i would say that it's not enough to just put the data out there in a consumable
format it needs to have context around it um and a lot of the times the producers of the
data itself have that context so these are um public servants who you know if you think about
urban planners and gis professionals um they're they're producing this data and they have very
valuable context and that can be communicated through narrative um i just worked on a project
actually uh in the bay area called vital signs which was with a nine county regional
transportation government that published all of its data so this was housing data transportation
data economic data um and the person the project manager on this project was was saying to me um
it's not enough just to dump our data out on the web anymore we have to make it meaningful
and it has to have an end user so i would say if we can get to a point where all data sets that
are published have metadata which basically just says where it comes from and how it was made
and when it was last updated um and then get to another level which is here's what it means to you
and here's how it's being used that would be so what's an example of that from your work at
coat for america an example of someone doing that well well this project that i was just mentioning
vital signs has done that well they have interactive charts maps um an actual new york
time style narrative around the published data so you can still download the raw format but you also
just you know you have that context to actually consume it so i'd say that that's a very good
example deep is that the kind of thing you would like to see or what do you want next from the
government as a constituent so i think is it's it's the exchange as you know we are talking about
what is the value of this data but when you talk about the data coming out and i was thinking you
know you can start publishing this data but with no relevancy on the frequency of the data is the
data getting updated on a daily basis and if you are publishing the data which is still six months
old what value it brings it to the table and it's defining the exchange so when we are talking about
example here the data comes out but what does it means to me i don't know so having those standards
so standard means where anyone can pick this data and say okay when we are saying this column has
this value this means this so that's to me is defining more standards so once we have the
standards where we know the common language where we can get this data and say oh great
this is in this format it is not pdf for sure no images you know i don't know if csv works here or
not but this is where i think technology tends to define those standards and this is one example
which i was giving early 90s when internet came up everyone started building their websites you
know it was in the beginning you know i start writing my own web pages eventually the challenge
what everyone faced was if i'm working here i have my own standard tomorrow i go and work
somewhere else i have my own standards suddenly we started forming groups where we say it's an
html within html these are the standards and now we live in a world where you write one piece of a
code you can render that on google chrome browser you can run on internet explorer you can run
anywhere else so that's that's the level what i think is we need to go into where we define
the common language which can be understand by everyone and then this data can be presented in
a very simple way to the consumer so i think defining those standards and how the data exchange
is happening is going to be the critical phase for this right so that came up earlier with the
transit data so everybody adopts the same standard google can make a thing for the whole country
i mean so ted what what do you see this in the city of alays data that has that same potential
what's the data you could standardize or make easier that 10 years from now is going to make
the city a different place to live and i think often when it ends up actually being is actually
cross-governmental so you know we could make all sorts of changes and improvements in our transit
data our crime data our 311 data etc but i think for the average citizen they really don't care
where the city of los angeles starts and stops versus the county of los angeles versus the city
of santa monica versus the city of beverly hills and so the idea where i say here's my data and
here it's classic government answer my my boundaries stop here you can't expect anything
more from me isn't the right answer so the more we can not just standardize data and come up with
some reasonable standards in a lot of ways conceptually the large cities could help really play a role
in that but to start to have more of a regional approach data in southern california or data in
california should in many ways be standardized if not how do you compare how do you compare
santa monica to los angeles to pasadena unless there's actually some comparability between them
so i think that's a very powerful very powerful mechanism and it goes from you know these infant
stages i think that the the the analogy to websites is a great one uh and in a lot of ways
open data takes kind of a tipping point you know folks get out there in fledgling ways and they
start making data available some of them start with pdfs and then people say not good enough
and so then they move right they move down the spectrum they start to provide more data
better data they start to have conversations with people who are doing civic hacking and they add
new types of data that they didn't even realize was useful i remember a conversation i had with
with sony worked for the federal government who said you would be surprised how much interest
there was in a wild donkey wild mule population in idaho here's a data set that was published that
half of us would think is completely irrelevant but there are some significant environmental
issues in idaho related to this population and only until they publish that type of data that
the average person would think is in many ways useless do they realize levels of interest so
it becomes very iterative it's a term we like to use when it comes to technology and software
development if you tell me to sit down and plan something out in the beginning i'll come up with
a very imperfect plan i'll take a shot at it but once i put something out then i have something
for people to poke holes at i can add changes to it i can modify i can improve it i could refine
it over time i think early on open data is people putting information out there refining it engaging
citizenry realizing that geography shouldn't be the limitations anymore and so i think hopefully
from our perspective is to improve and standardize data break geographical boundaries and really
become a lot more regional in the way we approach it and i think we'll probably uncover all sorts
of new issues as we do that and that's why i think the philosophical change in the conversation
is as powerful as anything if we keep trying to work down this road then we'll start to bring
those along who aren't interested we'll find folks in the region who don't even get it they
have no idea what we're talking about or or for some reason hiding something or whatever it may be
and i think that'll start to actually improve the conversation it'll become in a good way
bullying them in a good way it'll kind of make them it'll put them over on the side and they'll
be represented as a government who truly doesn't want to participate but only until you have
something of a tipping point can you really start to bring other folks along if not then it's just
the santa monica's and the federal government and and city of los angeles and those who are
progressively leading the way and we're just in some ways can still be seen as a minority uh and
one last question i'd add actually something similar to the secretary and then we'll go to
the audience and the questions you guys have sent in i mean share your vision i mean you have more
years in office and maybe you'll run for reelection and be secretary of state for eight years assuming
that happens or however it works out after that period of time uh how will this movement have
changed california or government or made things better and different what will the tangible
outcomes for people be well i i can't speak for governor brown but i think i'm excited about
the opportunities that i have in this in this new position of secretary of state so the most visible
part of my job is overseeing elections right so it's everything from the registration process to
what systems and equipment can be used for voting etc and uh there believe it or not there's a ton
of analytics it's possible in this registration rates turnout rates who's voting by mail who's
voting in person what time people are voting you know where they're voting that can help us
improve the voter experience right if we're starting with the customer uh in mind first
arguably the largest responsibility of my office is what we call the business programs division
anybody who's an entrepreneur here when you start it up you know the first step you needed to do
before you call the irs was to register your business with the state of california it's one
example of the filings that we do embarrassingly only a couple of transactions are possible online
with our office so by the time i'm done i'm hoping a lot of that is automated and not only am i eager
to get away from the dewy decimal system of business filings that we have to an online version
but i'm salivating at the data mining and analytics opportunities there are once we have
that digital and can share that data i mean you look at uh linkedin as an example and their
economic graph when they mine through employers and people looking for work and who's getting
hired educational backgrounds and all that imagine emerging that data with state government data of
businesses that are opening businesses that are closing with which industries and which zip codes
and cross-reference that with our employment development department of who's looking for work
and you know all of that then that can really help inform public policy and economic development
and issues at a statewide level at a regional and at a local level uh one other quick example i
mentioned the public finance piece earlier today but a really fun part of my job and i invite you
all to come to sacramento to visit the state archives the state archives fascinating collection
of official history official records official documents for the last 165 years since california
has been a state in this nation right starting with the original california constitution
unfortunately a very very small percentage of our archival collection is digitized imagine
what more cultural and educational value there would be if we shared things like old prison
records or early census logs or the original california constitution which by the way is in
both english and spanish a lot of people don't recognize things like that but the common theme
whether it's elections or archives or business filings or public campaign finance is this need
to just modernize because i've inherited an office that let's just say it's lacking in the
modernization front okay great okay so we're going to go to your questions from the audience
they're here on the screen i'm going to read them and if you guys really want to jump along
and just take it if not i'll pick somebody okay ready question number one question begins the
questions have surfaced about the accuracy of certain government data reports due to national
security constraints that are not disclosed to the general public how do we open data while also
protecting privacy and security i guess i'd put you well who could we ask that too ted how do you
protect people's privacy when you're opening data i can certainly do that i don't manage national
security but we do manage public safety and so a good example of is we maintain a lot of information
about city vehicles but if you had full access to the city vehicle database then technically you'd
have access to the vehicles that undercover police officers use right so here's an example
of a data set that i can't make fully available to you and so if not then basically any criminal
would have an understanding of that person is an undercover cop right because they know the license
plate and the type of car etc and that obviously puts those officers in a terrible position it puts
us as a city in a terrible position so i think usually my my my short answer is you know you
make all data available as much as possible and you try to restrain or constrain the items in
which you have a very valid compelling case and very compelling reason not to and when you do
you're simply making a subset of that data so we can make those types of data sets available we'll
need to pull them out so i think that's kind of the short answer to it but it also you know it
creates some pretty complex conversations and in our early steps to open data we knew we didn't
want to screw it up we knew that we could set things back five years if we started publishing
citizen social security information or information about undercover police officers or all these
kind of things that we would all agree as a terrible idea so it becomes very important to
be very good stewards to have multiple review processes and just to make sure ensure that
you're very clearly pulling things out that obviously are compelling not to be provided
okay question number two what advice would you offer to city and county officials who are
starting from scratch in the new world of open data maybe alicia you might be a good one for
that if you got sent off to to you know some random town in california then the mayor asked
you how do i do it what would you tell him well i think i would provide a few pieces of
pieces of advice i would say one is there's a huge community of like-minded municipal innovators out
there that you could tap into so find folks like these gentlemen on stage with me and talk to them
about how they did it would be one piece of advice but the other is something that i mentioned
before which is trace the data back to an end user if you want to open data don't do it just
to open data for data's sake only publish data after you've found a downstream audience to make
it actually valuable and useful for the public there's a person named mark head who's the former
cio of the city of philadelphia and he has a saying about what kinds of data a city should
publish first he says bucks buses and bullets and this is information that has real meaning to real
people but it's also data that can be used in applications that help people live their lives
better as a former city official you know not with my technology hat but my sort of political
head on to ask your constituents what information are they interested in right because you can
assume and talk to the to your counterparts in other cities and counties but you start releasing
data that the constituents aren't interested in there's a disconnect so just start by asking
and you know maybe you're able to deliver it first or easily or quickly or maybe not but you got you
can't underestimate the value of a public input can i will i'll add on this so i think one simple
advice is look into if what data being asked over and over again and how can we automate that
process so that we don't have to redo this if i go to office and every day if my manager is coming
to me and saying give this data or give me two hours i will get back to you and if i keep on
doing my job every day spend two hours i will rather go and find the ways to automate this
so always look for the ways how you can improve the efficiencies within an organization do
auditing of your past request and are there areas where after the auditing which you can automate
so that consumer can be self-serve rather than you serving them every time so that's another
advice i would give and and ben i don't mind making the offer if you're in the room feel
free to approach me i'll provide for you all the documentation all our policies and all of our
approach that we took at the city of la which i think might be able to give you some ideas and
if you're not in the room and let's say you're online or you're watching this at a late date
feel free to connect with ted ross at linkedin and we can go ahead and provide you all our
information you know we're we're strained like any other government but we believe so we believe so
much in this area that we're more than willing to make time with any county or state or city
who wants to know how we did at the city of los angeles because we just feel that much about it
as a national movement okay the next question is will the new laws compel police departments to
share crime data with the la times crime database so i'm the guy who built the la times crime
database so if you don't like it you can blame me afterwards and i think almost certainly the answer
is no to be honest with you the reality is is that crime reports data when you call up the police
and say you were robbed and that goes into their system right um are a public record and i can get
them or you could get them anyone can get them for the most part depending on what the cop you're
talking to by filing a public records request which is the separate set of laws that are i
think much more powerful that allow a citizen to request the data however those laws do not require
the process of delivery to be automated right or set up in a way that updates with any regular
frequency so if i file a public records request here in santa monica they could say they could
say well we have uh 14 days to respond and then we can ask for an extension and then at the end of
that time we will send you a cd in the mail that will have a spreadsheet on it that you can feel
free to put on the web and by the time i get that 30 days have gone by it's no longer as newsworthy
or as good and there's nothing in these laws that require data to be updated any more frequently
than that what allows our website to exist is that the la pd and the sheriffs department have taken
in my view the enlightened position right that they they're going to automate that process and
provide a machine readable feed that i can then write code and put into the database i'm sorry i'm
sorry let me hear that again you said los angeles la pd and the sheriffs department are doing good
job at that that well i have my complaints um so for instance maybe i shouldn't have opened the door
well for instance i would point out is that the enlightened approach is what i enlightened
approach that's what i heard well it is and it really is you know but they're not required to
and you know and and but it was something that we had to negotiate with outside the law and that
isn't my right or your right right and in the case of la pd they that in every department's going to
have their own reading of how that works currently and so you're going to get different results
depending on who you are and who you're talking to the la pd for instance uh has a reading of a
previous case law that says they're only allowed to they're only required to provide contemporaneous
records based on a 1990s judicial decision which they choose to read as six months so according
to the la pd they are only ever required to give you the most recent six months of crime reports
everything before is shielded from release and that's based upon a judicial decision
that said it's burdensome to go back and pull up those old data those old records well if they're
in a filing cabinet it might be but if they're an electronic database it's actually probably harder
to write the extra line of code to filter it out than to not right indeed can correct me here if i'm
getting you know wrong about that but about the tech part and so there's still a lot of barriers
to that stuff happening and i don't think that these laws are going to solve them and i think
it's still quite some ways away to be honest okay i'm off my soapbox i promise i won't do
that again our students our students someone's students whose students our students did a project
on city level garbage recycling and found some interesting results what are typical ways to share
these results with the government will the government publish data collected by private citizens
alex ted you can post on the mayor's facebook page
i think in probably you know the quickest answer is things like garbage collection is related to
our bureau of sanitation so i don't want to sound too governmenty but they're the ones who certainly
would have a very valid interest i think connecting with let's say a council member collecting with
your elected officials a great once again they're great representatives in city government
certainly that bureau of sanitation would have an interest and when it comes to the idea of
publishing private data well if it's compelling it's of value to other citizens then certainly
we would entertain it but we also want to avoid just the idea of just publishing all sorts of
things that as we start publishing let's say private citizen data onto a public portal it
starts to look as if it's official city of los angeles or official government records and so
that's such become you know kind of a dangerous kind of balance there so but i think more than
willing it's about sharing of data and making things open and available yeah and the l.a times
would if if if it if it meets our standards of course and we actually recently did some illegal
dumping analysis with similar data that found that there were disparities throughout the city
which has triggered we hope some changes and so data analysis like that is really becoming more
and more a part of investigative journalism in the world that i come from and so if you've got
students learning that stuff i am thrilled and they should consider a career in journalism i hope
so all right is there a question for ted is there a plan for citizens in l.a to be able to report
minor crimes online in a uniform format yes and what is that plan so we just recently did a there's
been multiple starts and stops when it came to some of these practices and the law issues they
ran to but we recently went through what we call an innovation fund effort so we have something
called the innovation fund we try to go ahead and invest in some of these projects and so in the last
few months they went ahead started that and so it was actually ideas that came in from various
city employees and they're very much in the process of being able to do that there's no reason
if you have a stolen bicycle or something like that that you need to come into a station to be
able to submit those and that's a part of actually a much larger effort we're doing where we're doing
digital services units where we're very actively and aggressively identifying ways and areas in
which people are filling out paper forms and they're standing in lines when they should be able to do
something online and do it on a mobile phone and so that's a very aggressive effort we're taking
we're big government so we're certainly trying to tackle all the different areas but yes that is
actually specifically an area that we've been working on the last few months and when can
people expect to see something like that roll out i'd have to check in with the folks who are
working on that that's actually not being done in my shop so so i would hate to commit them to that
but i certainly know it's something that has been funded in the last few months and
and i don't mind falling up on that but there was at least precursors to it if i recall correctly
you can report graffiti or potholes or absolutely things like that with uh taking a picture
with the mile a 311 mobile app versus Santa Monica folks you know won't be as useful but if you're
ever in the city of Los Angeles and Venice and otherwise you can download that app and you can
submit online requests 24 by 7 and they go through a great process i never like to call 311 i'm just
not the kind of person get on the phone but i use that app all the time and i can submit at any time
any place it's actually even better for the city it's a great example of where technology helps
the city because it's geocoded it's a great electronic record i've got an image of it
it's actually better than a phone call in when it comes to us and our ability to be able to service
the request a mile a 311 mobile app someone's got it right there excellent use it three times today
and and it and it begs that question right it's kind of like open data and sometimes we'll have
these conversations in government where someone in the room says but do we really want a bunch of
requests right do i want a bunch of requests and only in government would that conversation end up
happening what if i do what will i do if i get a bunch of requests well it means there's a bunch of
need right and and and that's the same conversation when it comes to open data but once again you know
it's easy for us from a consumer from a citizen perspective looking and say well that's a crazy
thing for them to say but when they're managing a department where every week they're given a
hundred units of work and they've got people to do 90 units of solution sometimes after you've been
doing that for a few years you may ask that question it's not the right question but i
understand why they'll ask that okay our next question is how can open data policy serve the
large population of angelenos and other californians who are functionally illiterate which might also
mean people who don't speak english i suppose too so how could open data help them does anyone
have an answer so i think is the defining the context of the open data is much more meaningful
in that context but you know it's rather than the california it's you know this data can be
master for example you know we all are expecting a linear year this time and you are illiterate
you are living in coastal area and we are predicting the huge rain or hurricane coming
towards your side can you use this open data which is collected by the weather
systems and make it more colorful and you know red yellow green red means run yellow means packed
and green means stay so i think there are ways to be we can do solve those problems because
there are people those who don't have cell phones they have no internet access you know so we we
need to find the ways and i like you know when there is a travel alert when we are traveling you
know this is red yellow so that's why government decided to go with the color scheme so that it's
easily understand by anyone rather than you carrying those devices and internet access so
i think that's that's the way we can mask the data and make it more meaningful to those people
and what i hear in that that to me i think came up a lot in the panel today is the idea of open
data being a vehicle for improving design within government even independent of data itself but
just designing the service in a more optimal or better way right so i mean alicia in your work
has it come up where you were trying to when you were thinking of your user with your human-centered
design right in the approach where your target user was someone who was either illiterate or
not an english speaker yeah i mean i can't speak to a specific example where that's happened but
certainly we've done a lot of work around access to public benefits so the cal fresh program which
is food stamps we worked on a project in san francisco where we really traced the process of
what a person has to go through to actually enroll in food stamps and they use many languages in
terms of the actual form you get that reminds you about the date that you need to have your interview
to be enrolled about the various things that you have to do to stay enrolled
and what we did by mapping out that process was actually provide data back to the administrator
of this benefit so that they could make changes to how they they actually administer their program
so one example of that and this was a form that was sent out i believe in cantonese
uh was had the date for the interview um that a person was required to be at
was after the date that it was actually sent to them and they just had no they just had no idea
that they were doing this um and we exposed the data to them and they they've stopped and they've
fixed that practice um so to get back to your point which is you can use data yes to consume
information but also to actually improve how government does its job uh similar logic um
you know there's it's been in the in the news in recent months this public policy proposal known
as new motor voter uh so i go back to the original motor voter from a couple decades ago
where based on federal law every state's required to offer a voter registration opportunity for
people when they're doing their business at dmv why because when you apply for a driver's license
or a state id or when you're renewing you're asked to update name address date of birth a signature
all the same information for voter registration so i have to go through the duplicate process
for people who are otherwise eligible 18 year olds and a citizen let's let's integrate not just a
driver's license renewal but a voter registration opportunity for efficiency purposes and the good
of democracy and so this new proposal you read about recently i'm proud we sponsored the bill
signed by the governor and we'll begin implementing here is now the the data sharing
between dmv and secretary of states for purposes of voter registration it's more efficient more
effective we're going to save taxpayer dollars okay next question is for deep how does a company
like trulia which is already a huge consumer of government data stand to benefit from a
comprehensive successful open data policy i would say in a in a huge way you know we've been
the biggest consumer of the public data for last 10 years and the more data we just talked about
the crime data here right why someone goes to trulia when they are trying to rent a property
or buy a home the first thing they look for is how is my neighborhood what's the crime score
what what's going on there and i think it is going to make better for us once the more data
is available to us more fresh data is there which is frequently updated we can consume this data and
reach out to our consumer and give them more information help them to make the right decisions
so i think it's going to help us in a big ways and it's we need to define you know i think
when i look into it i always look into the school now i i like to look into more drill down into
the school how the school has been performing as compared to other school which is just a mile away
from my home because that decision making process can help me buy a different home in a different
location so i think it's it's for us it's going to be much more meaningful and it's going to at
the end impact in a great way to our consumers because they are the one those who are at the end
consuming this data okay our next question is should governments and by extension the citizens
get something in return for providing open data to private businesses like trulia
that are making tons and tons of money off this presumably uh not necessarily dollars the person
asks but analytics intelligence new insights shouldn't they get something back yeah definitely
i i think it's profit is the side effect of solving a problem that's the way how the silicon
valley comes in but as i gave my own example should i rather go and spend my if i have to
buy a house should i spend six months doing all the research work finding a house which i want
or should technology helps and solve most of the problems for me and give that information for me
so rather than spending six months of my valuable time which i can go and spend and do other things
and rather spend just 15 days or one month to make that decision so in other way if you see
having that time back is the most valuable thing and that's what i look forward to is
how can i use technology to save five minutes here 15 minutes here and i think this is what
the technology is empowering me on a day-to-day basis when i was driving this morning from erwin
to santa monica is it gonna take me two hours or is it gonna take me one hour so not knowing that
information i can end up spending more time and the time to me at the end of the day is the money
i think philosophically i would first lean towards making the data available to various private
sector businesses to be able to facilitate you know economic development you know period so i
love that idea because usually what you find is that those companies are delivering real value to
you so you know tulia is a great example and there's many others you know when yelp gets
information from the county of l.a on health code standards and you check out a restaurant
and you see it's got an a a b or c you're getting value out of county data that was made available
to yelp and there's a lot of those examples of it but the question is also touching on something
which is another great point you know when we provide data to google for let's say way is data
related to you know parades and and street enclosures and all these other types of things
ways is also providing us what we call an api and interface to their data which means if i want to
know that there's an area of road in which maybe a pothole was logged that didn't come through the
my la 301 mobile app but it was actually done by a ways user and i've got let's say two thumbs up
if you've ever used that i now have basically three people confirming a pothole they're giving
us their information so that we could go ahead and consume it and do something off of that
information and once again you know these are great opportunities for us to do it so while i don't
expect a quid pro quo there's often opportunities that just come out and so as you start sharing
data and making data available you start to work with organizations and then do it with you
it creates once again that mentality and that mentality is a good one okay and now here's our
final question from the audience and then we'll close which is how can we evaluate the progress
of open data initiatives what would success look like anyone have an answer what success look like
so i think looking into the two bills what have been passed you know it's it's just having those
bills is not the success the success is are we publishing those enterprise systems what
data we've been storing is this so to me at the end of the day if we say this is the bill
are the local agencies standing behind this and publishing those so i will go back six
months down the line and go back and see if any data has been published if nothing has been
published to me that's not the success it means is going to take us another four years to even
publish those enterprise systems so that's the way i will consider at least success for this in
the scope of these two bills the way i think and i think it's not just you know which cities have
an open data policy which ones know which counties which states etc but you know whether it's five
ten years out just being able to quantify the amounts of data quality of the data and consistency
of the data because undoubtedly it will be used okay well you want to have something there Ted
you know yeah i'm never at a loss for words when it comes to this topic as you can tell
in working in city government often there's some pretty prescriptive ways to start to define it
and it comes down to some of the key benefits if you're looking at interdepartmental data sharing
then there's certainly benefits which you can track and see that various departments are sharing
data with each other and the results of that as part of our open data policy and our launch we
were able to close out various systems so we had various systems that were just there to create
a platform to share data by simply moving on to an open data portal and no extra charge you know
we were able to close out a 240 000 a year cost for sharing map layers between departments just
by putting it into our open data portal and allow them to share that there so there are areas in
which you could start to see return on investment when it comes to transparency that's a very
difficult one it's kind of hard to measure that but when it comes to let's say economics and
economic development etc sometimes you could start to point to that so you could run down a list it's
a pretty extensive one but you could run down a list of identifying key successes and I think
ultimately from government perspective it's weighing the cost it is to be able to run an open data
initiative both in the time it takes to do it as well as the platforms and the costs associated
with that with the benefits and I think quite often you know even if they're hard benefits
and soft benefits it truly does outweigh if you do it right open data is something that
you get a lot of bang for your buck and that's what we've seen at the city of LA
all right great so that's the end of our time here together round of applause for the panel please